<!-- 

  linalg.xml            cvec package documentation           Max Neunhoeffer

         Copyright (C) 2005, Lehrstuhl D für Mathematik, RWTH-Aachen

This chapter explains the mid-level linear algebra routines.

-->

<Chapter Label="linalg">
<Heading>Linear Algebra routines</Heading>

<Section Label="semiechelon">
<Heading>Semi echelonised bases and cleaning</Heading>

A semi echelonised basis is a record with the following components:
<C>vectors</C> is a list of vectors of equal length, optionally
(and optimally) they can be wrapped to a matrix. <C>pivots</C>
is a list of integers. The number <M>i</M> in position <M>j</M> indicates
that the <M>j</M>th vector in <C>vectors</C> has a one in column number
<M>i</M> and all vectors with a number bigger than <M>j</M> in <C>vectors</C>
have a zero in column number <M>i</M>.

<P/>
Note that for technical reasons another component <C>helper</C> is bound
containing a <C>cvec</C> of length <M>1</M> over the same field.

<P/>
Note further that the output of the &GAP; library operation 
<Ref Oper="SemiEchelonMat" BookName="Ref"/> is not compatible to this
setup, because it contains a component <C>heads</C> that contains at 
position <M>i</M>, if nonzero, the number of the row
for that the pivot element is in column <M>i</M>.

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="EmptySemiEchelonBasis" Arg="v"/>
<Returns> a new mutable empty semi echelonised basis </Returns>
<Description>
    The argument <A>v</A> must be a sample vector. Also a <C>cvecclass</C>
    can be given instead.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="MakeSemiEchelonBasis" Arg="b"/>
<Returns> a semi echelonised basis </Returns>
<Description>
    Turns the output <A>b</A> of <Ref Oper="SemiEchelonMat" BookName="Ref"/>
    into a valid semi echelonised basis in the sense of the 
    <Package>cvec</Package> package. This means that the component
    <C>pivots</C> is calculated from the component <C>heads</C>.
    Use this function only if necessary. Directly use 
    <Ref Meth="SemiEchelonRows"/> instead.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="CleanRow" Arg="b, v, extend, dec"/>
<Returns> <C>true</C> or <C>false</C> </Returns>
<Description>
    This is the basic operation for cleaning with a semi echelonised basis
    <A>b</A>. The vector <A>v</A> is cleaned with the vectors in the
    semi echelonised basis. The function returns <C>true</C> if <A>v</A>
    lies in the span of <A>b</A> and false otherwise. 
    <P/>
    The boolean
    value <A>extend</A> indicates, whether the basis should be extended
    in the latter case by the newly cleaned vector. 
    <P/>
    The argument
    <A>dec</A> is either <C>fail</C> in which case it is not used or
    a vector over the same field as <A>v</A> that is at least as long
    as the number <M>n</M> of vectors in <A>b</A> (plus one if <A>extend</A> is
    <C>true</C>). In this case, the first <M>n</M> components of <A>dec</A>
    are changed such that 
    <M>\sum_{{i=1}}^{n} <A>dec</A>_i <A>b</A>_i</M>. If <A>extend</A> is
    <C>true</C> and <A>v</A> is not contained in the span of the vectors
    in <A>b</A> and <A>dec</A> is a vector, then the first <M>n+1</M> 
    components of <A>dec</A> are changed such that 
    <M><A>v</A> = \sum_{{i=1}}^{n+1} <A>dec</A>_i <A>b</A>_i</M>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="SemiEchelonRows" Arg="m"/>
<Returns> a semi echelonised basis </Returns>
<Description>
    The argument <A>m</A> must be a <C>cmat</C>. This method calculates
    a semi echelonised basis for the row space of <A>m</A>. 
    <P/>
    There are a
    number of similar operations the names of which are derived from 
    <Ref Meth="SemiEchelonRows"/> by appending single letters: The letters
    <Q>P</Q>, <Q>T</Q> and <Q>X</Q> are modifiers and there are operations
    for most of the <M>8</M> combinations of those letters being present or not
    respectively. Always give the present letters in alphabetical order.
    <P/>
    The <Q>X</Q> indicates, that the input matrix may be
    destroyed, that is, the rows of <A>m</A> will be changed and the
    very same objects be used in the semi echelonised result basis.
    <P/>
    The <Q>T</Q> indicates, that the transformation is calculated, that is,
    the resulting record <C>r</C> will have a compontent <C>coeffs</C>, such
    that <C>r.coeffs * <A>m</A></C> is equal to <C>r.vectors</C> component
    of the semi echelonised result. Further, with given letter <Q>T</Q>
    there will be a component <C>relations</C> which is a basis for the
    (left) nullspace of <A>m</A>.
    <P/>
    The <Q>P</Q> indicates, that a component <C>r.p</C> is calculated such
    that <C>r.p * r.vectors</C> is the original matrix <A>m</A>.
    <P/>
    Currently the variants with <Q>P</Q> and <Q>T</Q> both present are not
    implement because they will probably not be very useful.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="SemiEchelonRowsX" Arg="m"/>
<Returns> a semi echelonised basis </Returns>
<Description>
    Same as <Ref Meth="SemiEchelonRows"/> but destructive in <A>m</A>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="SemiEchelonRowsT" Arg="m"/>
<Returns> a semi echelonised basis </Returns>
<Description>
    Same as <Ref Meth="SemiEchelonRows"/> but in addition stores the
    transformation, see <Ref Meth="SemiEchelonRows"/>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="SemiEchelonRowsTX" Arg="m"/>
<Returns> a semi echelonised basis </Returns>
<Description>
    Same as <Ref Meth="SemiEchelonRowsT"/> but destructive in <A>m</A>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="SemiEchelonRowsP" Arg="m"/>
<Returns> a semi echelonised basis </Returns>
<Description>
    Same as <Ref Meth="SemiEchelonRows"/> but in addition stores the
    inverse transformation, see <Ref Meth="SemiEchelonRows"/>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="SemiEchelonRowsPX" Arg="m"/>
<Returns> a semi echelonised basis </Returns>
<Description>
    Same as <Ref Meth="SemiEchelonRowsP"/> but destructive in <A>m</A>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="MutableNullspaceMat" Arg="m"/>
<Returns> a <C>cmat</C> </Returns>
<Description>
    Returns a <C>cmat</C> the rows of which are a basis of the (left) nullspace
    of the <C>cmat</C> <A>m</A>. Internally, <Ref Meth="SemiEchelonRowsT"/>
    is used and the component <C>relations</C> of the result is returned.
    The result is mutable, which is the reason for the introduction of 
    a new operation besides <Ref Oper="NullspaceMat" BookName="Ref"/>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="MutableNullspaceMatX" Arg="m"/>
<Returns> a <C>cmat</C> </Returns>
<Description>
    Same as <Ref Meth="MutableNullspaceMat"/> but destructive in <A>m</A>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="NullspaceMat" Arg="m"/>
<Returns> an immutable <C>cmat</C> </Returns>
<Description>
    Behaves exactly as expected. <A>m</A> must be a <C>cmat</C>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="NullspaceMatDestructive" Arg="m"/>
<Returns> an immutable <C>cmat</C> </Returns>
<Description>
    Behaves exactly as expected. <A>m</A> must be a <C>cmat</C>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>

<Section Label="polynomials">
    <Heading>Characteristic and minimal polynomial</Heading>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="CharacteristicPolynomialOfMatrix" Arg="m"/>
<Meth Name="CharacteristicPolynomialOfMatrix" Arg="m, indetnr"/>
<Returns> a record </Returns>
<Description>
    Calculates the characteristic polynomial of the <C>cmat</C> <A>m</A>
    over its base field. Because during the calculations the polynomial
    automatically comes as a product of some not necessarily irreducible
    factors, the result is returned in a record with two components.
    The <C>poly</C> component contains the full characteristic polynomial.
    The <C>factors</C> component contains a list of not necessarily 
    irreducibly factors the product of which is the characteristic polynomial.
    If an indeterminate number is given as second argument, the polynomials
    are written in that indeterminate, otherwise in the first indeterminate
    over the base field.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="FactorsOfCharacteristicPolynomial" Arg="m"/>
<Meth Name="FactorsOfCharacteristicPolynomial" Arg="m, indetnr"/>
<Returns> a list </Returns>
<Description>
    Calculates the characteristic polynomial of the <C>cmat</C> <A>m</A>
    over its base field. The result is a list of irreducible factors of
    the characteristic polynomial of <A>m</A>, the product of which is
    the characteristic polynomial. Because during the calculations the 
    polynomial
    automatically comes as a product of some not necessarily irreducible
    factors, this is more efficient than just calculating the characteristic
    polynomial and then factoring it.
    If an indeterminate number is given as second argument, the polynomials
    are written in that indeterminate, otherwise in the first indeterminate
    over the base field.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="MinimalPolynomialOfMatrix" Arg="m"/>
<Meth Name="MinimalPolynomialOfMatrix" Arg="m, indetnr"/>
<Returns> a polynomial over the base field of <A>m</A> </Returns>
<Description>
    Calculates the minimal polynomial of the <C>cmat</C> <A>m</A>
    over its base field. The polynomial is returned.
    If an indeterminate number is given as second argument, the polynomials
    are written in that indeterminate, otherwise in the first indeterminate
    over the base field.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Meth Name="CharAndMinimalPolynomialOfMatrix" Arg="m"/>
<Meth Name="CharacteristicPolynomialOfMatrix" Arg="m, indetnr"/>
<Returns> a record </Returns>
<Description>
    Calculates the characteristic and minimal polynomial of the 
    <C>cmat</C> <A>m</A>
    over its base field. Because during the calculation of the minimal 
    polynomial the characteristic polynomial is calculated anyway, the
    result is returned in a record with five components:
    The <C>charpoly</C> component contains the full characteristic polynomial.
    The <C>irreds</C> component contains the set of irreducible factors
    of the characteristic polynomial as a list. The <C>mult</C> component
    contains a corresponding list of multiplicities, that is in position
    <M>i</M> is the multiplicity of the irreducible factor number <M>i</M>
    in the characteristic polynomial. The component <C>minpoly</C> contains
    the minimal polynomial and the component <C>multmin</C> the corresponding
    multiplicities of the irreducible factors of the characteristic polynomial
    in the minimal polynomial.
    If an indeterminate number is given as second argument, the polynomials
    are written in that indeterminate, otherwise in the first indeterminate
    over the base field.
</Description>
</ManSection>
         
</Section>

<!-- ############################################################ -->

</Chapter>
